Guide to the William Henricks Wiser and Charlotte Viall Wiser Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
William Henricks Wiser and Charlotte Viall Wiser Papers
1836-2000
RG 128
Yale University Divinity School Library
13
(32 boxes + 1 portfolio)
William and Charlotte Wiser were Presbyterian missionaries in North India, appointed in 1915, and were active in the development of India Village Service, a demonstration project for the improvement of village life. These papers document the work of the Wisers in North India, particularly their involvement in rural reconstruction and their interest in Indian folklore.
Wiser, William Henricks, 1890-1961
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
William Henricks Wiser was born in Pennsylvania in 1890. He went to India under the auspices of the Board of Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. in 1915 after his graduation from the University of Chicago. Charlotte Viall joined him in India and they were married in Allahabad. William Wiser served on the staff of the Allahabad Agricultural Institute and as professor of rural sociology at the North India Theological College, Saharanpur. He also directed students in practical work in nearby villages. Charlotte Wiser also taught courses at the Allahabad Agricultural Institute.
Charlotte was born at Chicago, Illinois in 1892, and graduated from University of Chicago. She was sent as a Presbyterian missionary to India in 1916. She married William H. Wiser and they had three sons — Arthur, Alfred, and Edward. During their first term the Wisers were based in in Allahabad. During their second term(1925-1930), they worked in Mainpuri, and lived in the village of Karimpur, near Agra.
While on furlough in 1933, William Wiser completed a Ph.D. in rural social organization at Cornell University. Charlotte Wiser received a M.S. degree in nutrition from Cornell.
From 1945 to 1960 the Wisers were instrumental in the formation and direction of India Village Service, a demonstration project for the improvement of village life. William Wiser died in 1961 and Charlotte Wiser returned from India in 1970. Charlotte Wiser died in December 1981.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides valuable documentation of Presbyterian mission activity in North India. Much of of the correspondence, writings, diaries and printed material is related to rural India and the efforts of missionaries like the Wisers to improve the quality of village life.
As an avocation, William Wiser collected Indian folklore stories and songs. These stories and songs were told to native clerks who transcribed them in devanagari script. These transcripts were then copied in romanized Hindi, and finally translated into English.
Charlotte Wiser's active life as a woman missionary in rural India is well documented.
The first addendum (2010) includes material that Prof. Susan S. Wadley of Syracuse University used in her research regarding north India.
The second addendum (2104), which overlaps significantly with the early collection, provides additional documentation, particularly of the life and writings of Charlotte Wiser, and valuable early photographs and slides of India.
The series structure of the original collection has been changed to reflect the substantial additions.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1924-1976
II. Material related to India Village Service, 1934-1959
III. Material related to Indian folklore, n.d.
IV. Writings, 1836-1970s
V. Indian language material, n.d.
VI. Diaries and notebooks, 1912-1977
VII. Collected Material, 1877-1979
VIII. Biographical Documentation, 1915-1981, n.d.
IX. Audio-visual Material, 1913-1970s
Folklore -- India; Rural development -- India; Wiser, Charlotte Viall; Wiser, William Henricks, 1890-1961; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A -- Missions -- India
- Correspondence, 1924-2000; Series I
  - Original collection
    - Letters, 1924-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Correspondence is arranged chronologically. It includes letters from World Dominion Movement, International Missionary Council and Dorothy Parker, a missionary colleague (1951, 1952). Many of the letters describe village work during the time Dr. Wiser was director of India Village Service (1945-1960). Letter from Maurice L. Sill (1951) includes enclosure, "Colleagues in Action". Letters exchanged between Norvin Hein, Professor of Comparative Religion at Yale Divinity School, and Charlotte Wiser (1973, 1976) give information regarding the collection.
  - Addendum 2010
    - Letters to/from the Wisers and others, including re. Peace Corps, school, writings. One letter to Gardner Murphy from L.W. Bryce re. Conference on Social Tensions, 1939-1958 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Addendum 2014
    - Family correspondence, 1964-1981, no date (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Personal letters between CVW and friends incl. re, CVW trip to India and return, 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Personal letters between CVW and friends, 1973-1981 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Circular letters of Wisers, 1946, 1950 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Circular letters of others including from missionaries, including regarding CVW, 1972-1979 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - About Four Families book and filmstrips to/from CVW and Jean and Don Johnson, 1973-1978, no date (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - About Four Families book to/from CVW and Susan Wadley, 1977-1981 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - About Viability in Village of North India, 1978-1981 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Regarding work and continued involvement of CVW in India, incl. trip to India, speaking tour, financial support and legacy in village., 1958, 1971-1976 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence regarding village guesthouse project., 1972-1981 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence from Indian friends and villagers and others re. India, 1971-1980 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence incl. re. research assistance, letters from public, women's organizations, from Susan Wadley, 1949-1981, no date (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence regarding Yale Divinity Library Wiser Papers Collection, 1961, 1967, 1973-1981 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      includes 1961 correspondence from UNC Chapel Hill collection of Wiser papers
    - Notes and draft correspondence (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence of others, 1942, 1972, 1981, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Letters to/from William Wiser, 1934-1950 (Box 16, Folder 16)
- Material regarding India Village Service, 1934-1959; Series II
  - Reports, outlines, and notes relevant to the formation and development of I.V.S., 1934-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - 231 issues of "India Village Service", a bulletin issued by Wiser, 1934-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Material regarding Indian folklore, Series III
  Folders 7 through 20 contain transcriptions of Indian stories and songs; the originals are in Oversize, Drawer 3.
  - Original collection
    - Stories narrated by village people, no date (Box 2, Folder 8-14)
    - "The Mantras", no date (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous songs, no date (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Songs of Wazarin the Dancing Girl, no date (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - Khel Ke G t (eight songs in English translation); "The Story of Krishna" as told by a Kachhi (68 years old), no date (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Originals of materials relating to Indian folklore, no date (Box OVd3)
  - Addendum 2010
    - Songs and poems (transcribed and some translated by William Wiser), no date (Box 12, Folder 73-76)
    - Songs and poems (transcribed and some translated by William Wiser), no date (Box 13, Folder 77-89)
- Writings, 1836-1970s; Series IV
  - Original collection
    - Writings by the Wisers
      - Includes published and unpublished material, articles, reports, manuscript drafts, and two typescript copies of Behind Mud Walls in India, a study of a typical North Indian village which was later published in book form., 1925-1953, no date (Box 3, Folder 21-30)
      - Copies of published works by the Wisers: Behind Mud Walls (with reviews), For All of Life, The Hindi Jajmani System, Four Families of Karimpur (Box 6, Folder 45-46)
      - Copy of the prologue to The Four Families which gives biographical information about the Wisers. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Writings by others
      - Includes reports, statistics, minutes, newspaper clippings, all related to India (including on status of women). (Box 4, Folder 39-41)
      - Two papers by Prof. Susan Wadley of Syracuse University based on source material in the Wiser papers. (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Addendum 2010
    - Writings of Charlotte Wiser
      - Drafts, notes and copies of the Prologue and chapters of Four Families of Karimpur (by Charlotte Wiser, published by Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University, 1978) (Box 8, Folder 2-17)
      - Drafts and notes related to Four Families of Karimpur (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - "Brahmins" - drafts and notes, incl. stories of Ganesh; Ram Dayal (priest); Ramesh Lal (priest); Panditji's wife (Box 9, Folder 19-26)
      - "Brahmins of Karimpur" (Box 9, Folder 27-29)
      - "Farmers (Kachhis)" - the family of Parbat (Box 10, Folder 30-37)
      - "Oil Pressers (Telis)" - the family of Narayan; the sons of the Hakim (Rem Kishen) (Box 10, Folder 38-43)
      - "Oil Pressers" - family of Narayan (Box 11, Folder 44-46)
      - "Carpenters" - carpenters and the Jajmani system; the family of Devi and Balram; transcripts of tapes 1-5 and drafts (Box 11, Folder 47-53)
      - Crafts and other services (Box 11, Folder 54)
      - Festivals, incl. the Ramayan; Sivrati; the Holi Bonfire (Box 11, Folder 55)
      - Festivals, incl. Baksha - Bandhan; Tesu; notes on gods and festivals (Box 11, Folder 56)
      - Village stories - incl. "A Hindu Village Home in North India"; "Bahus" (Box 11, Folder 57)
      - Village stories - incl. "Bajrang Pulls His Family Up"; "Ganga Kshnan(Soron); "A Village Wrestling Match" (Box 11, Folder 58)
      - Drafts and notes on India incl. re. Moslems, industries, the people, Delhi, British rule, nationalism, food problems of a north India village, sanitation (Box 12, Folder 59-61)
      - "The Present Generation; the Younger Generation", 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 62-63)
      - "Their Children's Children", 1957 (Box 12, Folder 64)
      - Narration script for slides - "Behind Mud Walls", 1925-1975 (Box 12, Folder 65)
      - The foods of a Hindu village of North India, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 66)
      - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 12, Folder 67-69)
    - Writings of others
      - Student papers in Indian language (Box 12, Folder 70-71)
      - India Village Service (pamphlet) (Box 12, Folder 72)
  - Addendum 2014
    - Writings of William Wiser
      - By-Products of a Village Survey, c. 1925 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - How Village Christians Live, 1925 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - The Need for a Christian Economic Liberties League, no date (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Jamanji (1), 1932 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Jamanji (2), 1932 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Social Institutions of a Hindu Village in North India: An Abstract of a Thesis, 1933 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - The Economics of Poverty, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Research Studies in the Economic and Social Environment of the Indian Church, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 8)
        A Study of 23 Christian Rural Groups in the Urbnited Provinces; A Study of 31 Urban Churches in the United Provinces.
      - Building the Social and Economic Foundations for an Indigenous Church in the United Provinces, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Financial Foundations For the Church in Rural Areas, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - other writings (Box 17, Folder 11)
        "A Palace Wedding," "The Missionary in Relation to Social Organizations," "Community Life With A Christian Bias": unpublished, excerpted, and/or date unclear.
    - Published writings of Charlotte Wiser
      - The Passing of a Faithful Disciple, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - The Foods of a Hindu Village of North India, 1933 (Box 17, Folder 13)
        Thesis, original
      - The Foods of a Hindu Village of North India (Copy) (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Presenting "For All of Life" in Your Society, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 15)
        original and carbon copy with notes
      - Veteran Observer of Rural Life Watches Generation Gap Touch Families in Her Indian Village, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 16)
        essay by Charlotte Wiser as told to Betty Baird
    - Writings of William and Charlotte Wiser
      - May We Come In?, 1926 (Box 17, Folder 17)
        Charlotte Wiser's reflections/report on first year survey later incorporated into Behind Mud Walls
      - Behind Mud Walls (copy), 1930 (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Behind Mud Walls Publishing Contract and Copyright, 1930, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - Behind Mud Walls drafts for second edition by C. Wiser (Box 17, Folder 20)
      - Behind Mud Walls notes and fragments for second edition by C. Wiser (Box 17, Folder 21)
      - Indian Village Service: Retrospect and Prospect, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Indian Village Service: Retrospect and Prospect (source documents), 1940s, 1950s (Box 18, Folder 2)
        Director's Reports outlined (1-49; #29 missing, #5 "Roundtable Discussion"); "A New Village Project for India" (1944); IVS circular letter (1946); correspondence regarding continued support for IVS (1947); drafts.
      - Reports on their work, 1939, 1940, 1949, no date (Box 18, Folder 3)
        Including annual report written from the perspective of the Wisers' car.
    - Unpublished writings/drafts of Charlotte Wiser
      - Creative Writing assignments, English 4 & 5, 1923 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - The Wedding of Ilachi and Ralla Ram (a play), 1923 (Box 18, Folder 5)
        includes programme, draft with notes, Sanskrit language materials.
      - Creative writing/narrative nonfiction drafts, 1920s (Box 18, Folder 6)
        includes correspondence from C. Wiser to Martha Smalley/Yale Special Collections (1980) and several drafts of "All For a Son" and other pieces. Gives clues into genre (fiction/nonfiction) and writing process.
      - Narrative nonfiction, no dates (Box 18, Folder 7)
        includes later creative writing course (Extension 122) with urgent reflection on purpose of writing ("having been out of the country for so long, it's hard to know what readers care about... it is a serious matter for us now. I must write to sell, if I can". A later piece makes reference to retirement cruise.
      - Festivals, 1960s (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - My Indian and American Family, 1960s, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        drafts, reflections, notes on family
      - Village Life and Simple Living, no date (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - Viability of the Village in Contemporary Society, 1977-1979 (Box 18, Folder 11)
        notes, AAAS symposium presentation (February 1978) and paper (1979)
      - Viability of the Village in Contemporary Society, 1977-1979 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - Excerpt of report re. missions, 1931 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - Notes for Fulbright orientations, 1957, 1960s (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - Notes for Peace Corps orientations, 1960s (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - Women's Association presentation notes, 1960s (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - Notes for presentations, 1960s-1972, no date (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Four Families key terms, c. 1978 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        Actual and fictitious names used in Four Families and on slides; draft references, glossary, summary of families.
      - Four Families Introduction (draft), 1974 (Box 19, Folder 2)
        With corrections. Found with letter to Dr. Hein (Oct 74) and letter to Dale Ward making reference to "carbon copy of introduction".
      - Four Families Introduction (earlier drafts) (Box 19, Folder 3)
        "superceded by later versions"
      - The Family of Parbat, Farmer (bound) (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - The Family of Parbat, Farmer (mimeographed copy) (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Farmers (draft) (Box 19, Folder 6)
        likely for editor/publisher with original photographs (not in book)
      - Carpenters (draft) (Box 19, Folder 7)
        missing first page
      - The Oil Pressers (final draft) (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Brahmins (draft) (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Farmers, crop chart (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Farmers, first draft (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Farmers, draft (Box 20, Folder 3)
        includes family tree
      - Farmers, draft (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Farmers, draft (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Farmers, draft (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Farmers, draft (Box 20, Folder 7)
        30 years later, 1969, consolidation
      - Farmers, draft (Box 20, Folder 8)
        1969, consolidation
      - Farmers, editor's notes (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Carpenters, draft (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Carpenters, draft (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Goldsmiths, and other sketches re. village life (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Oil Pressers, draft (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Oil Pressers, draft (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Brahmins, draft (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Brahmins, source documents, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 7)
        census, correspondence, information on wedding and notes
      - Brahmins, notes (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Bards (Box 21, Folder 9)
        notes, "village general", "village viability"
      - Four Families, mixed drafts (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Four Families, mixed drafts (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Four Families, diary notes, typed, 1957-1967 (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Preface, draft by Susan Wadley (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - Stories re. Dana, Umesh, Ovais, notes, and correspondence, no date (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Notes/fragments by Charlotte Wiser
      - Maloja Parish Council Rules for Scavenger Hunt (Box 22, Folder 1)
        program bulletin with notes
      - notes re Hinduism and language (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - notes re Tagore (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - notes re calculation of horoscope (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - notes re Sanskrit vocabulary lists (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Hinduism and Sanskrit practice notebooks (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Hinduism and Sanskrit practice notebooks (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - notes re craft of writing (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - notes re India, villagers (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - other notes (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Writings of others
      - Journal of Lady Fanny Parks (typed excerpt), 1836 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Letter by American Missionaries exploring N. India, 1836 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Writings by Prem Chand Lal, President, Mayo College Ajmer (Box 23, Folder 3)
        Two original documents; personal reflection on experience as president of college and an exegesis of the 23rd Psalm
      - Unpublished essay/letter by Prem Chand Lal and colleague on America, American Missions, no date (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Writings re missions Indian, other, general, 1936, 1937,1941, 1944, no date (Box 23, Folder 5)
        One Hundred Years by Arthur Judson Brown (excerpt); "A Vital Village Church," by Janki Parshad (essay, original); book reviews published in The Christian Century (original) (with handwritten notes by C. Wiser); Without the Camp (pamphlet) by The American Mission to Lepers, Inc Missionary Study Outlines for use with "For All of Life" and "We Who Are America" (pamphlet, original); Christian Missions and Point IV by Division of Foreign Missions NCCC (includes article re Wisers) (newsletter, original)
      - Communications in Village India (book) by Selden C. Menefee and Audrey G. Menefee, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 6)
        handwritten on cover, "For Charlotte Wiser from [co-author] Selden Menefee"
      - India Through Literature (pamphlet) by Donald and Jean Johnson, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Four Families book reviews, 1978 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Presentations by Douglas Ensminger, 1980, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - YMCA of Delhi Report re Jaffarpur Women's Cooperative Industrial Society, 1980, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 10)
        original including letter of explanation to Gov't of India Ministry of Social Welfare (1981)
      - Presentations by Susan Wadley, 1980, 1981, no date (Box 23, Folder 11)
        Sent to Charlotte Wiser; "Deceitful and Faithful-- Cunning and Victimized: Contrasting Images of Karimpur Women" "Cunning in the Courtyard: Women in Karimpur Folktales", "The Katha of Sakat: A Study in North Indian Narrative Strategies"
      - Presentations and publications by Susan Wadley (Box 23, Folder 12)
        Sent to Edward Wiser with related correspondence (1982-2000)
- Indian Language Material, Series V
  - "Nur Duniya men Aya"; story with translation (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
  - "The Story of Krishna" as told by a Kachhi (68 years old) (see Series III) (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
  - Four Posters; including political campaign poster in Hindi language, poster representing Christ, replication of wall painting. (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
  - Booklets used in literacy classes in urban Service work in Karimpur (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1912-1970s; Series VI
  - Original collection
    - Diaries and Notebooks of Charlotte Wiser, 1934, 1942-1945, 1947, 1964, 1967, 1970, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Diaries of Charlotte Wiser, 1912, 1913-1916, 1965, 1967, 1968, 1969, 1971, 1976, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Diaries and Notebooks of William Wiser, 1934, 1941-1945, 1947, 1949, 1950, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 107)
    - Karimpur Diaries; Journals and notes, 1927-1929, 1948 n.d. (Box 4, Folder 31-38)
    - Notes for talks given by CVW, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Addendum 2014
    - Pocket diary, fieldnotes, houses #1-58; #59-117; #118-166, 1926-1927 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 2 Pocket diaries, socioanthropological notes, study sheet music, 1927 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Pocket diary, socioanthropological notes, 1935 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Fragment of diary, re first village tour, 1939 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Day planner, incl re IVS visits, work, travel, 1946 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Fieldnotes, Census of Karim Ganj, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Excerpt from diary, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 7)
      Typed excerpt from diary (Jan-Aug 1970) incl. re retirement and continued work in America and India
    - Notebook, notes incl re village life, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Day planners, personal, 1962, 1973, 1975, 1978, no date (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Excerpts from diaries, re village life, 1920s-1960s (Box 24, Folder 10)
- Collected Material, 1877-1979; Series VII
  - Original collection
    - Large Indian fan made of cloth (Box OVd3)
    - Indian fan made of cloth (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - 3 models of Indian implements (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Addendum 2010
    - Related to Presbyterian mission in north India
      - Incl. statement by William Wiser; names and addresses of Mission board members; document in Indian language, 1926-1945 (Box 13, Folder 90)
      - Minutes of Annual Meetings (North India Mission), 1945-1946 (Box 13, Folder 91)
      - Minutes of United Provinces Christian Council, 1947 Nov (Box 13, Folder 92)
      - Minutes of 90th Annual Meeting; the Synodical Board, 1948 Jul (Box 13, Folder 93)
      - Minutes of Executive Committee; Annual Meeting, Christian Council, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 94)
      - Incl. minutes of Annual Meeting, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 95)
      - Minutes of miscellaneous committees, 1943-1950 (Box 14, Folder 96-98)
    - Collected material
      - Agricultural glossary (Box 14, Folder 99)
      - Memorandum on Agriculture in the District of Cawnpore, 1877 (Box 14, Folder 100)
      - Delhi Training and Orientation Centre for Foreign Technicians in Inda - catalogs, 1955-1958 (Box 14, Folder 101-103)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Addendum 2014
    - Collected materials
      - The Gist of the Lesson: A Concise Exposition of the International Sunday School Lessons for the Year 1918 (book) by R.A. Torrey (Box 25, Folder 1)